<div align="center"><font face=1><br>
 <br>
 <br>
THE MARINER'S GUIDE TO ENCHANTED VESSELS<br>
<br>
A Complete Guide to Rowboat Operation<br>
<br>
<br>
<font face=5>Being a comprehensive manual for the proper use and maintenance of enchanted watercraft, as approved by the Imperial Maritime Guild<br>
<hr>
<div align="center"><font face=1>Forward<br>
<br>
<div align="left">Congratulations on your acquisition of a genuine Cyrodiilian rowboat! Whether you seek the tranquil waters of Lake Rumare for an afternoon's fishing, or dare to brave the treacherous channels of the Niben Bay, this sturdy vessel shall serve as your faithful companion upon Tamriel's waterways.<br>
<br>
This manual, penned by the master shipwrights of the Imperial City, contains all knowledge necessary for the proper operation of your enchanted craft. Study it well, for the waters of Cyrodiil can be as unforgiving as they are beautiful.<br>
<hr>
<div align="center">Chapter I: Basic Operation<br>
<br>
<div align="left">Your rowboat has been imbued with minor enchantments that respond to both physical and magical commands. There exist two primary methods of propulsion:<br>
<br>
The Art of Rowing<br>
<br>
The most traditional method employs the "Row" spell, which you discover upon touching your vessel for the first time. When cast, this spell channels your stamina into forward momentum, as if you were pulling mighty oars through the water. Should you wish to reverse direction, simply adopt a crouched stance while casting - the enchantment will understand your intent and propel the craft backward. Those of hearty constitution may maintain the spell's casting for extended periods, though take care not to exhaust yourself completely whilst far from shore!<br>
<br>
Enchanted Propulsion<br>
<br>
For those who prefer to conserve their strength, your boat responds to verbal commands. Simply touch the vessel's hull and speak your intent - whether to "row forward" or "row backward" - and the boat's enchantments will maintain steady progress without further effort on your part.<br>
<hr>
<div align="center">Chapter II: Navigation and Steering<br>
<br>
<div align="left">The boat's enchantments are attuned to your gaze and intent. When standing upon the deck, simply look in your desired direction of travel, and the vessel will gradually turn to match your heading.<br>
<br>
<font face=5>Note from the Enchanter's Guild: Those who favor the perspective of eagles - viewing themselves from above - must physically orient their body in the desired direction, as the enchantment cannot divine intent from such a vantage.<br>
<br>
<font face=1>Maintaining Course<br>
<br>
Should you wish to observe the scenery whilst maintaining your present heading, touch the hull and speak the command to "lock heading." The boat will then maintain its course regardless of where you turn your gaze. To restore normal steering, simply command it to "unlock heading."<br>
<hr>
<div align="center">Chapter III: Overland Transport<br>
<br>
<div align="left">Through clever application of levitation enchantments, your boat may be transported across dry land - though not without considerable effort! To engage this feature, touch the hull and express your desire to "drag the boat." You may also trigger this enchantment through casting the row spell while near the boat.<br>
<br>
Be warned: the boat's full weight of two hundred pounds will rest upon your shoulders during transport. Many a sailor has found themselves caught by bandits or wild beasts whilst so encumbered! You may release the boat at any time by dropping it from your pack or touching the hull once more.<br>
<hr>
<div align="center">Chapter IV: Summoning Your Vessel<br>
<br>
<div align="left">Through the application of advanced translocation magics, your boat may be called to your location from great distances. This enchantment proves invaluable when your vessel becomes lodged amongst rocks or when you simply cannot recall where you moored it last evening.<br>
<br>
Standard Summoning<br>
<br>
The primary summoning ritual calls your boat to the most suitable location before you. The enchantment's intelligence will seek solid ground or calm water, avoiding obstacles that might damage the hull. Simply speak the summoning command when not upon the boat, and it shall appear at a safe distance ahead.<br>
<br>
Direct Placement<br>
<br>
For those situations requiring precise positioning, a secondary command exists to place the boat directly before you. Be warned - this method bypasses the enchantment's safety measures! Your boat may manifest suspended in mid-air or partially merged with solid objects. Use this method only when the standard summoning proves inadequate.<br>
<br>
<font face=5>A word of caution: The translocation process requires several moments to complete. Do not attempt to board your vessel until it has fully materialized and settled into position.<br>
<hr>
<div align="center"><font face=1>Chapter V: Maritime Enhancements<br>
<br>
<div align="left">Master Sergius Verus of Three Brothers Trade Goods in the Imperial City's Market District offers several improvements for the discerning mariner:<br>
<br>
Rowboat Storage Chest<br>
<br>
A waterproof strongbox enchanted with preservation magics. Any items stored within shall remain safe from both thieves and the ravages of time. Unlike common containers, this chest will never mysteriously empty itself of your possessions.<br>
<br>
Rowboat Lamp<br>
<br>
A specially crafted lamp that provides illumination during night voyages. It may be lit or extinguished by touch, through the boat's command system, or by application of fire and frost magics respectively. Let flame kindle the wick, or frost snuff it out!<br>
<br>
Rowboat Rope Ladder<br>
<br>
A rope ladder imbued with protective enchantments. Should you fall overboard whilst the boat moves through open water, this ladder will automatically deploy, allowing you to regain the deck. A wise investment for those prone to maritime mishaps!<br>
<hr>
<div align="center">Chapter VI: Safety and Maintenance<br>
<br>
<div align="left">General Precautions<br>
<br>
Always ensure you are within reasonable distance of your vessel when attempting to row. The enchantments cannot reach beyond approximately three hundred feet.<br>
<br>
Your boat will cease all movement should you find yourself overboard, save for when the safety ladder deploys.<br>
<br>
Take care when navigating shallow waters or near shorelines - your boat may become grounded upon rocks or sand.<br>
<br>
The boat's enchantments prevent operation whilst seated in meditation or rest. Stand ready at the helm!<br>
<br>
Collision Detection Peculiarities<br>
<br>
The protective enchantments that prevent your boat from merging with solid matter can occasionally prove... temperamental. You may find your vessel suddenly "grounded" whilst in open water - fear not! This is merely the enchantment being overly cautious. Simply continue rowing and the boat will free itself.<br>
<br>
Conversely, these same protections may sometimes slumber when most needed, allowing your boat to become lodged within cliff faces or other obstacles. Should this occur, employ the summoning ritual to recall your vessel to a clear location.<br>
<br>
Navigation and Location<br>
<br>
Fear not losing track of your vessel! The boat bears a minor cartographic enchantment that marks its position upon your map whenever it comes to rest. Look for its marker when you need to retrieve your craft.<br>
<br>
Boarding Your Vessel<br>
<br>
The standard boarding command attempts to place you atop the deck, though the enchantment sometimes miscalculates, depositing you in the water instead.<br>
<br>
A more reliable method involves using the boat's seat - this forcibly positions you aboard, though in a seated position.<br>
<br>
Those who have invested in the safety ladder may activate it whilst the boat is stationary for the same reliable boarding as the seat.<br>
<br>
Choose your method based on circumstances and how wet you're willing to become!<br>
<br>
Interior Waterways<br>
<br>
Be especially cautious when navigating caves, grottos, and other enclosed spaces with water. The boat's water-level detection enchantments can become confused by the conflicting magical auras common to such places. Your vessel may behave erratically, believing itself to be on dry land whilst clearly afloat, or vice versa.<br>
<br>
A Final Word of Wisdom<br>
<br>
Should you encounter any behavior not described in this manual, remember that your boat is a complex marriage of carpentry and enchantment. Like any magical artifact, it may occasionally surprise even its creators. When in doubt, disembark, summon the vessel anew, and approach with patience and good humor.<br>
<hr>
<div align="center">Appendix: Advanced Enchantment Modifications<br>
<br>
<div align="left"><font face=5>The following section is intended only for those versed in the highest arts of maritime enchantment. Improper modification may result in unstable or dangerous vessel behavior.<br>
<br>
<font face=1>For those brave souls who would tune their vessel's enchantments, speak the ancient console invocation (`) and recite:<br>
<br>
ObvConsole set RYB.ENCHANTMENT to VALUE<br>
<br>
To understand the current state of your vessel's enchantments, scry all current enchantment values by reciting:<br>
<br>
sqv RYB<br>
<br>
Movement Enchantments:<br>
BoatMaxVelocity (6) - Maximum speed attainable<br>
BaseRowForce (0.05) - Force applied when rowing<br>
BaseTurnRate (0.4) - Base turning speed<br>
TurnDeadzone (10) - Degrees before turning begins<br>
VelocityDecayLnRetentionFactor (-0.01005) - Speed depletion rate<br>
TurnRateAcceleration (0.15) - Turn start speed<br>
TurnRateDeceleration (0.92) - Turn stop speed<br>
<br>
Dragging Enchantments:<br>
DragRopeLength (250) - Distance before boat follows<br>
DragMaxVelocity (4.0) - Maximum dragging speed<br>
DragFriction (0.85) - Resistance when dragging<br>
DragZInterpolationRate (0.1) - Speed of height adjustment<br>
DragBaseTurnRate (0.1) - How quickly boat turns<br>
DragMaxTurnPerFrame (2.0) - Max speed of boat turns<br>
DragTurnDeadzone (5) - Degrees of diversion before boat turns<br>
DragLandPlayerZOffset (30) - Height of boat off ground<br>
DragTurnRateAcceleration (0.15) - Turn start speed<br>
DragTurnRateDeceleration (0.92) - Turn stop speed<br>
DragPathSlopeFactor (0.7) - Tilt angle sensitivity<br>
DragPathSlopeDeadzone (2) - Minimum slope of land to tilt<br>
DragMaxPitchAngle (45) - Maximum tilt angle on slopes<br>
DragPitchSmoothingFactor (0.15) - Smoothness of tilting<br>
DragPathMinDistance (50) - Distance to drag before adjusting tilt<br>
DragUphillZAdjustmentFactor (6) - Amount to lower boat dragging uphill<br>
DragDownhillZAdjustmentFactor (6) - Amount to raise boat dragging downhill<br>
<br>
Wave Simulation Enchantments:<br>
RockingEnabled (1) - Enable water motion effects<br>
RockAmplitudeZ (0.8) - Vertical rocking magnitude<br>
RockAmplitudePitch (2.0) - Forward/back tilt magnitude<br>
RockAmplitudeRoll (3.0) - Side-to-side tilt magnitude<br>
RockFrequency (30.0) - Primary rocking speed<br>
RockFrequency2 (30.0) - Secondary rocking speed<br>
RockFrequency3 (30.0) - Tertiary rocking (roll) speed<br>
RockWeatherFactor (0.5) - Weather influence multiplier<br>
RockSpeedFactor (0.25) - Boat speed influence multiplier<br>
RockDistanceThreshold (3000) - Distance from boat rocking ceases<br>
RockSmoothingFactor (0.1) - Smoothness of rocking<br>
<br>
Weight Distribution Enchantments:<br>
PlayerWeightEnabled (1) - Enable weight effects<br>
PlayerWeightPitchFactor (0.15) - Forward/back tilt from position<br>
PlayerWeightRollFactor (0.12) - Side tilt from position<br>
PlayerWeightSmoothingFactor (0.2) - How fast tilt changes<br>
PlayerWeightMaxDistanceForward (240) - Distance lengthwise effect applies<br>
PlayerWeightMaxDistanceSide (100) - Distance sideways effect applies<br>
PlayerWeightMaxDistanceVertical (60) - Distance upwards effect applies<br>
<br>
Collision Detection Enchantments:<br>
CollisionDetectDelay (2) - Delay before checking obstacles<br>
CollisionDetectZThreshold (10) - Height threshold for collision<br>
ColliderOffset (300) - Distance forward from center for detection<br>
ColliderOffsetReverse (350) - Distance backward from center for detection<br>
ColliderMoveFreq (0.05) - How often to move collider<br>
OverboardDistance (300) - Distance before "overboard" triggers<br>
<br>
Miscellaneous Enchantments:<br>
SummonDistance (350) - Distance boat appears when summoned<br>
LandZThreshold (40) - Height above water considered "on land"<br>
WaterLevelZ (0) - Base water level<br>
DeltaSmoothingFactor (0.1) - Sensitivity of frame rate compensation<br>
<br>
<font face=5>May fair winds and following seas guide your journeys across Cyrodiil's waters!<br>
<br>
Published by the Imperial Maritime Guild Third Edition, 3E 433<br>